# 大家好 最近天氣很乾燥哦
Hi everyone! It's very dry recently.
# 攝影小哥又上火啦
Mr. Cameraman is "shang huo" (lit: too much internal heat) again.
# 我去挖點那個野生的葛根
I'm gonna dig some wild kudzu roots,
# 葛根給他
kudzu roots, and make a,
# 燉湯潡湯
make a soup for him,
# 下下火
to "xia huo" (lit: reduce the internal heat)
# 就在那河邊 河邊不還
It's just on the riverside, the riverside, not too far away.
# 我要過去看一下
Let me take a look on the other side.
# 好像是有
There seems to be some.
# 很危險的哦 這裡
It really dangerous here.
# 這就是葛根 你看 剛長出來的小藤 很小的這個藤
This is kudzu root. Look! It just came out from the earth and is still young and small.
# 來 把它挖出來
Alright! I'll dig it out.
# 請勿模仿
DO NOT IMITATE
# 這個太危險了 這裡
It's too dangerous here.
# 請勿模仿
DO NOT IMITATE
# 下面的水潭哦
It's a pond down there.
# 挖到一個
Here's one.
# 被我搞爛了
I've broken it.
# 你看 這個就是
Look! This is,
# 這個就是葛根 就那麼小一點點
this is a kudzu root, just a tiny little bit.
# 搞到搞不到
It doesn't move an inch.
# 後面還有根
Back there is still a root.
# 先把它根砍掉
Let me chop off the root first.
# 終於挖出來
Finally...
# 你看 這被挖爛啦 這裡也挖爛啦
Look! It's broken here, and here too,
# 這裡也挖爛啦
and here as well.
# 沒辦法 這個太難挖啦 長到那石頭下面去
Well, anyway. It's growing into the rocks and it's just too hard to dig it out.
# 像不像人蔘 這樣
Does it look like a ginseng? See?
# 拿回去煲湯
Let's bring it back and make a soup.
# 很好吃的哦 這個
It's very tasty, you know.
# 哎呦 這個刺
Ayo! The spikes,
# 刺人啊
they sting.
# 看一下其它地方還有沒有
Let's see if I can find any more in other places.
# 這裡有哦 (註︰英文很少這樣說，為免太Chinglish，變了一下說法)
Oh yea!
# 出來啦 出來啦
Here it is, here it is.
# 你看 終於把它挖出一點點來啦
Look! Finally a tiny little bit is coming out.
# 你看
Look!
# 這個可以啦
This is good enough.
# 又被我搞爛了一點
I've broken it again.
# 這裡被我砸了一下 嘖 沒辦法
I've knocked on here. Well, anyway.
# 夠大
It's big enough.
# 夠啦 兩條
We have two now. It's enough.
# 準備回家
We're heading back now.
# 你看 這個葛根 我洗乾淨啦
Look! The kudzu roots. I've washed them already.
# 給竹鼠聞一下 給它吃一下
I'll show it to the bamboo rats, let them smell and taste it,
# 看它喜不喜歡吹
and see if they like it.
# 要不要吃
You wanna have some?
# 很好吃的哦
It's really tasty,
# 是吧 你看 它吃了
isn't it? Look! It's eating.
# 我也很想吃啊
I love it too.
# 下去
Let's go,
# 燉了
and boil it.
# 你看 有點小毛哦
Look! There's still some hair.
# 我們上火裡面燒一下它
Let's burn it in the fire.
# 已經可以啦
It's alright now.
# 你看 這樣輕輕刮一下
Look! It can now be easily cleaned,
# 就很乾淨了
by a gentle scratch.
# 把這個葛根放下去
Let me put the kudzu roots into the pot.
# 這個是我們山上引上來的水哦
This is the water diverted from our hill.
# 搞點生薑下去
Put some ginger.
# 一點點
Just a bit.
# 一點點就夠啦 不要那麼多
Just a bit would be enough. We don't need too much.
# 加點鹽
Put some salt.
# 倒不出來
It's not coming out.
# 好 可以 夠了
Okay! Alright! It's enough.
# 因為現在
Cuz now,
# 秋天 秋天天氣比較乾燥
it's autumn, it's autumn and it's rather dry,
# 不能野外生火哦 所以我們就在家裡把它燉啦
we can't set a fire in the wild. So we'll just boil it at home.
# 最少要煲兩個小時
It takes at least two hours.
# 把這個蓋蓋下
Cover it with the lid.
# 等一下就可以吃了
Then we can enjoy it in a while.
# 哇 燉了兩個小時哦
Wa! It has been boiled for two hours.
# 嘖 應該差不多啦
It should be alright now.
# 先嘗一下
Let me have a try.
# 搞塊被吃一下
Have a piece of skin.
# 嗯
Um!
# 很好吃哦
Tasty!
# 好燙
Very hot!
# 小狗 一二三四五
Doggies one, two, three, four five,
# 六
six
# 誰吃
Who wants?
# 誰搶到就誰的
Who got it, who have it.
# 嗯 這個野生的葛根就是好吃
Um! The wild kudzu roots are always tasty.
# 但是竹鼠更好吃
But bamboo rats taste even better,
# 特別是它的皮
especially the skin.